Today we have assembled here
امروز اینجا جمع شده‌ایم
to celebrate the Diwali, the Deepavali.
که دیوالی را جشن بگیریم، دیپاوالی را.
Actually, only after Sahaja Yoga started,
در واقع فقط بعد از این که ساهاجایوگا شروع شد،
the real Diwali is taking shape.
دیوالی راستین دارد شکل می‌گیرد.
We had many beautiful lamps,
ما چراغ‌های زیبای بسیاری داشتیم
and we had lot of oil to burn,
و روغن‌ زیادی که بسوزانیم،
but there was no spark, to enlighten the deepas.
اما شعله‌ای نبود که دیپاها را روشن کند؛
And the wick, as you call it is called as bati in Hindi language
و آنچه شما "فتیله" می‌نامید و هندی‌ها "باتی" می‌نامند،
is like your Kundalini,
شبیه کندالینی شما است.
so the Kundalini had to meet the spark.
پس کندالینی باید با شعله تماس می‌یافت،
The beautiful lamps were all a waste, purposeless, pointless.
چراغ‌های زیبا همه بی‌‌فایده و بی‌هدف و بیهوده بودند؛
And this is the great blessings in modern times,
و این رحمت بزرگ زمانه جدید است،
that so many lights are enlightened
که چراغ‌های بسیار زیادی روشن شده‌اند
and we are having a Deepavali of human hearts.
و ما داریم دیپاوالی قلب انسان‌ها را جشن می‌گیریم.
When you become the light, you don’t worry about the lamp,
وقتی به نور تبدیل می‌شوید، نگران این نیستید که چراغ
how it looks, how it is to be made,
چطور به نظر می‌آید و چطور قرار است ساخته شود؛
it’s all done.
همه انجام شده است.
You just have to worry about the flame, about the oil,
فقط باید به فکر شعله باشید و به فکر روغن.
because it’s the oil that burns and gives light.
چون این روغن است که می‌سوزد و نور می‌‌دهد.
In Sanskrit language, which is the language of the Gods,
در زبان سانسکریت که زبان ایزدان است،
the oil is called as ‘snigdha’, ‘snigdha’;
روغن را "اسنیگدها" می‌‌نامند،
is something that is soft but is snigdha.
یعنی چیزی که نرم است، با این حال اسنیگدهاست
And ‘sneha’ means ‘friendship of love.
و"اسنیها" یعنی دوستی عشق؛
And the poets in other languages have used this word,
و شاعران از این کلمه در زبان‌های دیگر هم استفاده کرده‌اند.
in different way calling it ‘neha’.
به شکل دیگری که به آن "نِها" می‌گویند.
They have sung the praise of this love.
آنها آوازهایی در ستایش این عشق سروده‌اند.
Every poet, every Saint
هر شاعر و عارفی
has used this word in their beautiful poetry,
از این کلمه در شعرهای زیبایش استفاده کرده است.
whether they were in separation or they were in the meeting, in the yoga, in the union.
چه در فراغ بودند و یا در وصال، در یوگا، در یگانگی؛
This love is the thing that gives the light.
این عشق است که روشنایی می‌‌دهد.
If this oil is not clean, contaminated,
اگر این روغن تمیز نباشد و آلوده باشد،
you get the smoke.
دود می‌‌کند؛
but is pure,
اما اگر تمیز باشد،
then it gives a brilliant light without any smoke.
نور درخشان بدون دودی ایجاد می‌کند.
But when this oil is fragrant
اما هنگامی که این روغن معطر باشد،
then the light gives the fragrance as well.
نور هم به همان اندازه، بوی عطر می‌دهد.
The oil is made from various things.
روغن از مواد مختلفی درست می‌شود.
The one that comes from the Mother Earth cannot be used
چیزی که از مادر زمین آمده باشد را نمی‌‌شود استفاده کرد.
because it’s very materialistic, it gives carbon.
چون وابسته به ماده است و کربن می‌دهد.
Like petrol, kerosene, it pollutes the atmosphere.
مثل بنزین و نفت سفید که هوا را آلوده می‌‌کند.
Then the one that comes from animals,
بعد آنچه از حیوانات گرفته می‌شود،
who are – some of them, are very much worshipped in India,
حیواناتی که بعضا در هند خیلی ستایش می‌شوند،
they have a very particular type of snigdha
آنها نوع خاصی از اسنیگدها،
or we can call it ghee or oil
یا به قولی گی یا روغن دارند،
which is giving a light which is very soothing and peaceful.
که نوری آرامش‌بخش و تسکین‌دهنده می‌دهد.
So when matter evolves into animal state
پس وقتی ماده به حیوان تکامل یابد،
also the oil evolves.
روغن هم تکامل پیدا می‌کند.
But when this oil is rubbed onto the feet of a Saint,
اما وقتی این روغن به پاهای یک قدیس مالیده شود،
it gets the fragrance.
عطر پیدا می‌کند؛
In the same way if this oil is brought in contact with flowers
به همین شکل اگر این روغن در جوار گل‌ها قرار بگیرد،
it gives fragrance.
خوشبو می‌شود.
So the feet of a Saint are like the flowers on the tree.
پس پاهای یک قدیس شبیه گل‌های روی درخت است؛
And when the flower falls on the ground, the Mother Earth,
و وقتی که گلی روی مادر زمین می‌‌افتد،
it’s so delicate, it’s so sensible, it doesn’t hurt Her.
آنقدر لطیف و خردمند است که به او آسیبی نمی‌زند.
It falls with great reverence
با احترام فراوانی فرو می‌افتد،
as a great homage to the Mother Earth.
گویی مادر زمین را تجلیل فراوانی می‌کند.
In the same way a Saint has to be gentle,
به همین شکل، یک قدیس باید آرام باشد،
gentle in the way the moonlight falls upon this Earth.
به ملایمت مهتابی که بر زمین می‌‌افتد.
It is light without any burning in it, no scorching.
این شعله‌ای است که نه سوزندگی در آن است و نه داغی.
That gentleness one has to develop,
انسان باید به این ملایمت برسد.
out of the oil that is the love in your heart,
از آن روغنی که همان عشق درون قلب‌های شماست؛
which lubricates everything,
که همه چیز را روغن‌کاری می‌کند،
which removes the frictions
که اصطکاک را از بین می‌بَرد
and soothes.
و تسکین می‌دهد.
You have seen the way nature works.
شما دیده‌اید که طبیعت چطور کار می‌‌کند.
We never see a flower opening out,
ما هرگز شکفتن گل‌ها را نمی‌بینیم،
we never see the fruit coming out of the flower.
هرگز بیرون آمدن میوه از گل‌ها را نمی‌بینیم.
It is so gentle and so slow
آنقدر ملایم و آرام است،
that the movement is not seen by these human eyes.
که حرکتش با چشم انسان دیده نمی‌‌شود.
Because the Nature wants you should not be disturbed by the movements.
چون طبیعت نمی‌‌خواهد با حرکت‌هایش مزاحم شما شود.
The Nature cares, so you people do not feel the growth,
طبیعت مراقب است شما رشد،
the movement and the explosions of the evolution
حرکات و هیاهوی تکامل را حس نکنید
or we can say the movement of Nature’s own behavior.
و یا می‌توان گفت حرکات ناشی از رفتار خود طبیعت را؛
In the same way a Saint, a Sahaja Yogi,
به همین شکل یک قدیس یعنی یک ساهاجایوگی،
has to move very smoothly in the society of Sahaja Yogis.
باید خیلی آرام در جمع ساهاجایوگی‌‌ها حرکت کند.
It is with the Sahaja Yogis, I said; not with the non-Sahajas.
این را برای ساهاجایوگی‌ها گفتم، نه برای غیرساهاجایوگی‌‌ها.
Nature reacts to anything that is foreign.
طبیعت به هر چیز خارجی واکنش نشان می‌‌دهد.
It throws out anything that is not Sahaj.
او هرچه را که ساهاج نیست، بیرون می‌‌اندازد.
In the same way, a Saint should not accept
به همین شکل یک قدیس نباید هیچ چیز و هیچ‌کسی را که با رفتار ساهاج بیگانه است، قبول کند.
When it deals with the matter, with the materialistic people,
وقتی با ماده و افراد مادی‌گرا سروکار دارد،
then it acts with the greatest wisdom, as the tip of a root.
همچون نوک یک ریشه با بیشترین خرد عمل می‌کند.
It moves with majesty,
با شکوه حرکت می‌‌کند،
embeds itself into the Mother Earth
خودش را در مادر زمین جا می‌‌دهد،
going round all hard rocks
دور سنگ‌های سخت می‌پیچد
and holding them together;
و آن‌‌‌‌ها را کنار هم نگه می‌دارد
it makes the tree to stand up erect.
و باعث می‌شود درخت در زمین روی پا بایستد.
The sign of life is that
نشانه زندگی آن است که
it goes against the matter, the one that is "jara".
خلاف ماده حرکت می‌کند؛ آن‌ که "جارا" است.
Like the tree goes against the gravity;
مثل درخت که خلاف جاذبه حرکت می‌کند.
like the great human beings have lifted their body
همچون انسان‌های بزرگی که قامتشان را برخلاف جاذبه راست می‌کنند،
In the same way, if you see, the flame
به همین صورت اگر شعله را نگاه کنید،
goes against the gravity.
می‌بینید خلاف جاذبه حرکت می‌کند.
Nobody has heard of fire going from the top floor to the ground floor.
هیچ‌کس نشنیده که آتش از طبقه بالا به طبقه پایین بیاید.
It starts from the ground floor and it goes upward.
بلکه از طبقه پایین شروع می‌شود و به بالا می‌رود.
But the fire also comes from the matter which is burning.
اما آتش هم از ماده‌ در حال سوختن ایجاد می‌شود.
So the matter has to be burnt, if you want to rise.
پس اگر می‌‌خواهید بالا بیایید، ماده باید بسوزد.
If your attention is all the time towards baser things,
اگر توجه شما همیشه روی چیزهای سطح پایین،
materialistic things, towards physical pleasures,
امور مادی، مسائل دنیوی و لذت‌های فیزیکی باشد،
you cannot rise.
نمی‌توانید رشد کنید.
You may do any amount of meditations, use My Photographs, come to My Pujas,
هر مقدار هم که مدیتیشن کنید، عکس مرا بگذارید، به پوجای من بیایید،
but if your attention is imbedded
ولی توجهتان درگیر باشد،
it’s like you are standing on a crocodile trying to get into a boat.
مثل آن است که برای سوار شدن به قایق روی یک تمساح بایستید.
Now, that doesn’t mean when a flame burns,
حالا بدین معنی نیست که وقتی شعله می‌سوزد،
it gives up matter,
دست از ماده می‌کشد؛
but it gets detached and it burns it.
بلکه رها می‌شود و آن را می‌سوزاند.
So this body,
پس این بدن،
this mind,
این ذهن،
this ego,
این ایگو
this superego,
و این سوپرایگو،
is all to be burned to keep this flame burning all the time.
همه باید بسوزند تا این شعله را همواره روشن نگه دارند.
You don’t have to give up anything,
لازم نیست از چیزی دست بکشید،
but to use the same thing for a higher life,
بلکه لازم است که از آن برای زندگی والاتری استفاده کنید؛
and that is what should be the aim of every Sahaja Yogi.
و این باید هدف هر ساهاجایوگی باشد.
Actually after getting Realization,
در واقع بعد از گرفتن خودآگاهی،
you just start spontaneously giving
شما خودبخود دست می‌کشید،
because you are the light.
چون نور هستید.
But respect your light and the light of others.
اما به نور خود و دیگران احترام بگذارید.
The darkness is too much
تاریکی خیلی زیاد است
and we need so many lights
و ما برای از بین بردن این تاریکی به نورهای خیلی زیادی نیاز داریم.
These lights are to be maintained, to be looked after,
این شعله‌ها را باید نگهداری و مراقبت کرد
to be loved.
و به آن عشق ورزید.
As you know very well,
همان‌طور که خوب می‌دانید،
I cannot do it alone.
من نمی‌توانم این کار را به تنهایی انجام دهم.
For example the source of electricity, if you use to burn,
مثلا اگر از مبدأ اصلی برق برای روشنایی استفاده کنیم،
you may have a big explosion.
احتمالا انفجار بزرگی روی خواهد داد.
It has to go to various bulbs
باید به لامپ‌های مختلف برود
to give a nice, spread-out light.
تا نوری زیبا و فراگیر به وجود آورد؛
And you are the channels,
و شمایید که کانال هستید،
you are the ones who are going to express Me.
شمایید که قرار است مرا نشان دهید.
I am just the potential energy,
من فقط انرژی پتانسیل هستم.
as the energy is coming from somewhere which is stored
همان‌طور که انرژی از جایی می‌آید که ذخیره شده است،
and if I asked you,
اگر از شما بپرسم انرژی شما از کجا می‌آید، حتی نمی‌دانید کجا ذخیره شده است.
It is through your behaviour,
از طریق رفتار شما،
through your pure lights,
از طریق نور پاک شما
through your fragrance,
و از طریق رایحه‌ شماست که
people are going to know God Almighty.
مردم قرار است خداوند متعال را بشناسند.
There are some, which can blacken the Face;
هستند کسانی که می‌توانند چهره را سیاه کنند.
they are lights no doubt,
آنها بدون شک شعله‌اند،
but can blacken the Face
ولی می‌توانند چهره را سیاه کنند.
if there are impurities,
اگر ناپاکی وجود داشته باشد،
blacken the Face of the Divine,
چهره خدا را سیاه کنند،
blacken the Face of your Creator.
چهره آفریدگار شما را سیاه کنند
And that is what, one has to be careful,
و این چیزی است که شخص باید مراقبش باشد،
that we are not blackening the Name of God by our misbehaviour.
که نام خدا را با رفتار بدمان خدشه‌دار نکنیم.
Now listen to Me very carefully,
حالا به من خوب گوش کنید.
If there is no light out of the lamp,
اگر از چراغ نوری حاصل نشود،
it does not blacken nor enlighten.
آن چراغ نه سیاه می‌کند و نه روشن می‌کند.
But if there is a light,
ولی اگر نوری باشد،
it can blacken as well as enlighten.
می‌تواند علاوه بر روشن کردن، سیاه هم بکند.
It’s only the Sahaja Yogis who
این فقط ساهاجایوگی‌ها هستند که
can blacken or enlighten the Name of God Almighty.
می‌توانند نام خداوند متعال را سیاه یا روشن کنند.
Say, for example, if you have a fake man,
مثلا اگر آدم دغل‌بازی وجود داشته باشد،
he doesn’t blacken the Name of God
نام خدا را خدشه‌دار نمی‌کند،
because he is himself black,
چون خودش سیاه است.
so nobody’s bothered about that.
برای همین کسی اهمیت نمی‌دهد.
If there is a person who is teaching about God
اگر کسی باشد که در مورد خدا آموزش بدهد
or talking about God, about religion
یا درباره خدا و مذهب صحبت کند
and making money out of it,
و از این راه پول درآورد،
he blackens his own name.
او نام خودش را خراب می‌کند.
He does not blacken the Name of God Almighty.
نام خداوند متعال را خدشه‌دار نمی‌کند.
The Name of God, cannot be blackened,
نام خدا را نمی‌توان خدشه‌دار کرد،
It’s ever shining.
همیشه می‌درخشد.
But it’s only a Sahaja Yogi
ولی فقط یک ساهاجایوگی است
which can form that cloud to cover It.
که می‌تواند نام خدا را با ابری که ایجاد می‌کند، بپوشاند.
They can only finish the hope of this world.
آنها هستند که می‌توانند امید این جهان را ناامید کنند.
They can only bring the real destruction of this world.
فقط آنها هستند که می‌توانند نابودی واقعی را برای این جهان به ارمغان بیاورند.
They will be held responsible.
مسئولیتش به دوش آنها خواهد بود؛
And they should be punished in time,
و آنها هستند که باید به موقع تنبیه شوند،
so that the Name of God should not be ruined.
تا نام خدا از بین نرود.
For they have been given the right to enter into the Kingdom of God,
چون به آنها حق ورود به قلمروی خداوند داده شده است.
others are outside.
بقیه بیرونند.
They are the only ones who can abuse the right.
فقط آنها هستند که می‌توانند از این حق سوءاستفاده کنند.
Those who are outside this building, cannot spoil it.
آنها که بیرون این ساختمان هستند، نمی‌توانند آن را خراب کنند.
You have the special privilege
امتیاز ویژه‌ای که شما دارید این است که
to enter into this beautiful building.
می‌توانید وارد این ساختمان زیبا شوید.
You have got this right because of the great things you have done in previous lives.
شما این حق را به خاطر کارهای بزرگی که در زندگی‌های قبلی‌تان انجام داده‌اید، به‌ دست آورده‌اید؛
And if you now want to spoil it,
و اگر الان بخواهید آن را از بین ببرید،
you’d better understand that you will be very severely punished.
بهتر است بدانید که به شدت تنبیه خواهید شد.
The light which can enlighten can also burn.
شعله‌ای که بتواند روشن کند، از عهده سوزاندن هم برمی‌آید.
But this light will burn all those who try to burn the Kingdom of God.
اما این شعله تمام کسانی را که در پی سوزاندن قلمروی خداوندی هستند خواهد سوزاند.
So on a Diwali day let us know that
پس در روزی چون دیوالی بدانیم،
we should have the lamps, burnt in such a way that
چراغ ما باید طوری بسوزد که پاک‌ترین عشق پاک خدا، در آن شعله‌ور باشد،
Not a lip service, lip service of love,
نه فقط به زبان، نه عشق زبانی،
but from your heart.
بلکه از قلبتان،
It should pour,
این عشق باید سرازیر شود؛
like the Nature pours all its blessings upon you.
همچون طبیعت که رحمتش را بر سر شما می‌ریزد.
Then, wherever the flowers of your feet will touch,
بعد گُل پاهای شما به هر جا برسد،
the Nature will blossom with joy.
طبیعت با شادمانی شکوفا می‌شود.
There will be a Deepavali.
آنجا یک دیپاوالی خواهد بود.
Like I was told when, before coming to Rome, Italy had no rain.
مثل قبل از آمدن من به رُم؛ که گفتند در ایتالیا باران نمی‌آید.
The Mother Earth was parched.
مادر زمین خشک شده بود
And as soon as you all Sahaja Yogis came on this Mother Earth,
و به محض اینکه شما ساهاجایوگی‌ها بر این بخش از مادر زمین پا گذاشتید،
it started pouring.
باران سیل‌آسا شروع شد.
So the purity of love is to be understood with complete discretion,
پس پاکی عشق را باید با بصیرت کامل درک کرد.
because this purity acts;
چون این پاکی اثر می‌کند.
it acts in the nature, it acts in the human beings, it acts into everything.
پاکی در طبیعت، در انسان و بر هر چیز اثر می‌گذارد.
The action is the same as the action, the gentle action of the Mother Earth.
تأثیر آن مانند عملکرد آرام مادر زمین است.
Those who come in contact with such a personality
کسانی که با چنین شخصیتی تماس پیدا می‌کنند،
start suddenly feeling the soothing, the settling, of the whole being, into a blissful state.
ناگهان احساس آرامش در کل وجودشان ایجاد می‌شود و آنها را به حالتی سرشار از رحمت و برکت می‌رساند.
into a blissful state.
حالتی سرشار از رحمت و برکت،
State of benediction.
حالت نیایش.
But I don’t know, after this word, how much has gone wrong,
ولی نمی‌دانم با این کلمه چقدر اشتباه شده است؟
because our words are corrupt.
چون کلمات ما فاسد هستند.
Our words are corrupt,
کلمات ما فاسد هستند.
they do not express what they mean.
معنای خودشان را بیان نمی‌کنند.
They are not also pure.
آنها خالص هم نیستند.
They do not reflect what is to be reflected.
آنها آنچه را که باید، منعکس نمی‌کنند.
So, it is for us to create new meanings of the words,
پس بر ماست که معنای جدیدی برای کلمات خلق کنیم.
give a clear vision.
تصویر شفافی به وجود آوریم.
When you want to see a clear vision,
وقتی می‌خواهند تصویر شفافی ایجاد کنند،
you put a powerful light before the mirror.
نور پرقدرتی را جلوی آینه می‌گذارند.
Clear vision of the expression in language, in gestures, in behaviours;
تصویر شفافی از هر آنچه در زبان، قیافه و رفتارهاست به وجود آورید؛
and a clear vision of the Divine.
و تصویر شفافی از خداوند.
Let people see in your light,
بگذارید مردم با نور شما ببینند
the beautiful dream coming true.
رویاهای زیبا به واقعیت می‌پیوندند.
In My childhood I used to think My dreams are too fantastic.
در کودکی  تصورم بر این بود که رویاهایم بیش از حد تخیلی هستند.
Will they ever materialize?
آیا بالاخره محقق می‌شوند؟
I used to collect small, little stones.
من همیشه سنگ‌های کوچک جمع می‌کردم
And I would say:
و می‌گفتم:
“Will there be people, who are not the stones but who are the hearts?”
"آیا می‌شود بعدا کسانی را یافت که نه سنگ، بلکه قلب باشند؟"
By God’s grace, I have met you.
به لطف خدا شما را دیدم.
I thank you very much
از شما خیلی ممنونم،
for accepting Sahaja Yoga.
که ساهاجایوگا را پذیرفتید.
But this invitation that is extended to you
ولی این دعوتنامه‌ای که برای شما تمدید شده،
should not be such that, I will be blamed
به هیچ وجه نباید مایه ملامت من شود،
for giving it to people who never deserved it.
اینکه چرا آن را به افرادی که هرگز شایستگی نداشته‌اند داده‌ام.
Please do not let Me down.
لطفا مرا ناامید نکنید.
There’s one small thing,
نکته خیلی کوچکی هست،
I come from a country
من از کشوری آمده‌ام
which is not so sophisticated in the modern world,
که در دنیای جدید خیلی پیچیده نیست.
but is very much embedded in Truth,
اما بسیار در حقیقت جاافتاده است؛
and I’m happy you respect that country despite
و خوشحالم که به این کشور هرچند طبیعی و غیرمدرن است، احترام می‌گذارید
and you are proud of a Mother who comes of such a country.
و به مادری که از چنین کشوری آمده افتخار می‌کنید.
This is the Deepavali which is celebrated in that country
این دیپاوالی است که در آن کشور هزاران هزار سال است که جشن گرفته می‌شود؛
And this is the first time in Rome,
و این اولین بار برای رم است،
which is the center of Europe.
که مرکز اروپا است.
Because here is the seven hills,
چون اینجا هفت تپه وجود دارد،
expressing the whole of seven chakras.
نماد تمام هفت چاکراست.
That is why a big torch had to be brought from England in an aeroplane
برای همین با هواپیما باید مشعل بزرگی با هواپیما از انگلیس آورد،
to enlighten these seven chakras of Europe.
تا این هفت چاکرای اروپا را روشن کند.
The Kundalini rises from mooladhara and goes up to the seventh chakra
کندالینی از مولادهارا برمی‌خیزد و به سمت هفت چاکرا بالا می‌آید
and touches the Sadashiva’s place
و به جایگاه ساداشیوا می‌رسد؛
but in this case from Sadashiva’s place, the light has come down,
ولی در این حالت نور از جایگاه ساداشیوا پایین آمده
to enlighten and respect all the chakras from their heart.
تا تمام چاکراها را از مرکزشان نورانی کند و به آنها احترام بگذارد.
In the beginning of the awakening of the Kundalini, that’s what exactly I do,
هنگام بیدار شدن کندالینی، دقیقا نظیر کاری که من می‌کنم،
is through your fingertips, the awahana, the invitation to the Kundalini, is sent.
از سرانگشتانتان، "آواهانا" یعنی دعوتنامه‌ برای کندالینی فرستاده می‌شود.
Unless and until it passes through these centers
تا زمانی که از این مراکز عبور نکند،
it cannot open it out sufficiently for the Kundalini to rise,
نمی‌تواند آنها را به قدر کافی برای بالا آمدن کندالینی باز کند؛
and then the Kundalini rises.
و بعد کندالینی بالا می‌آید.
So the invitation first has to come from the heart chakra here.
پس دعوتنامه باید اول از چاکرای قلب، اینجا بیاید.
So the desire has to come down first of all,
پس اول آرزو باید فرود آید.
the power of desire has to come down, from the heart,
قدرت آرزو باید از قلب فرود آید
to make the Kundalini rise.
تا کندالینی را مجبور به بیدار شدن کند.
So the Kundalini acts,
بدین ترتیب کندالینی عمل می‌کند،
the power of action takes place.
قدرت عمل پدیدار می‌شود.
So the responsibility of England
پس مسئولیت انگلستان
and the responsibility of Europe is very great.
و مسئولیت اروپا بسیار بزرگ است.
Unless and until all these chakras are cleared,
تا وقتی این چاکراها پاک نشوند،
Vishuddhi cannot be pushed aside.
ویشودی را نمی‌شود کنار زد.
So we have to consolidate first in Europe and also in England.
پس ما اول باید در اروپا و نیز در انگلستان مستحکم شویم.
I started it in England then in Europe.
من اول از انگلستان و بعد اروپا شروع کردم.
Once we have consolidated it well,
وقتی به خوبی مستحکم شویم،
I’m sure Sahaja Yoga will be very easily established in America.
مطمئنم ساهاجا یوگا در آمریکا هم خیلی آسان تثبیت می‌شود.
India there’s no problem, as you know;
همان‌طور که می‌دانید، هند مشکلی ندارد
and that is going to work out very easily
و این کار به راحتی انجام می‌شود؛
and once India is awakened
و همین که هند بیدار شود،
the Kundalini will start moving very fast, with great dynamism.
کندالینی خیلی به سرعت و با قدرت زیادی شروع به حرکت می‌کند.
But first these upper chakras must be put right.
ولی اول باید چاکراهای بالاتر درست شوند،
Otherwise how can Kundalini come out?
وگرنه کندالینی چطور می‌تواند بالا بیاید؟
So, you realize your responsibility,
پس شما مسئولیت خودتان را می‌فهمید.
that we have a force in India, no doubt.
که ما یک نیرویی در هند داریم، شکی نیست؛
But how will it rise if there are obstructions?
ولی با وجود موانع، چطور می‌تواند بالا بیاید؟
You are a part and parcel of this universe,
شما بخشی از این دنیا هستید،
you are not hanging somewhere else from India,
شما دور از هند، در هوا معلق نیستید.
so India has to depend on you.
پس هند ناچار است به شما وابسته باشد.
For your sahasrara I have already made all arrangements
برای سحسرارای شما من از قبل، ترتیب همه چیز را داده‌ام.
in the sense I am here in person.
یعنی شخصا اینجا حاضرم.
I have come down from Kailasha, on this Earth.
من از کایلاش بر زمین فرود آمده‌ام.
So, that’s how I have arranged the whole drama.
اینطوری کل نمایش را ترتیب داده‌ام.
But the middle actors are very important.
اما بازیگران وسط صحنه بسیار مهم هستند.
They should not act like clowns
آنها نباید مثل دلقک‌ها بازی کنند
or stupid idiotic people.
یا مثل آدم‌های خنگ احمق.
It is becoming quite idiotic, the atmosphere, I must say,
باید گفت فضا دارد کاملا احمقانه می‌شود.
you feel as if you are among idiots or lunatics.
آدم احساس می‌کند انگار بین احمق‌ها یا دیوانه‌هاست.
So, these ridiculous things that are happening around us should not impress us
پس نباید تحت تأثیر موارد احمقانه اطرافمان قرار بگیریم،
but we should really use them for amusing ourselves.
بلکه باید از آنها برای سرگرمی خودمان استفاده کنیم؛
And you have reached that ascent
و شما به آن رشدی رسیده‌اید
that you can see these things are coming there because of the decadence.
که می‌توانید ببینید، این مسائل به خاطر فساد پیش می‌آید
And the decadence is the ruin, is the destruction of the chakras also.
و فساد یعنی تباهی و نیز نابودی چاکراها.
So though it is stupidity, idiocity,
پس با آنکه حماقت و بلاهت در جریان است،
we have to pick up people out of them,
باید افراد را از بین آنها برچید،
to support the chakras.
تا چاکراها را بشود پشتیبانی کرد
And to be very careful with the people who are not Sahajas
و باید خیلی مراقب افراد غیرساهاجی بود
who are sticking on in Sahaja Yoga.
که دارند به ساهاجایوگا می‌چسبند؛
And now the time has come to throw them out permanently and they are not to return back.
و حالا وقتش رسیده که آنها برای همیشه بیرون انداخته شوند. طوری که دیگر برنگردند.
Only the veeras, the courageous, can worship the Mother.
فقط "ویراها" یعنی دلاوران، اجازه دارند مادر را ستایش کنند
And I hope you are all that,
و من امیدوارم شما همه آن‌گونه باشید
and today is the great day
و امروز روز بزرگی است،
when I am worshipped by all the veeras and veeranganas.
چرا که ویراها و ویرانگاناها به ستایش من آمده‌اند.
May God bless you all.
رحمت خداوند شامل حال همه شما باشد.